Guide to the Barbara Hope Cooper papers, 1969-1999
Cooper, Barbara Hope papers, 1963-1999
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Barbara Hope Cooper papers, 1969-1999
14-22-3072
Barbara Hope Cooper, 1953-1999
6.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notes, calculations, materials for talks, data collection information, publication drafts and reprints, and course materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes research and teaching materials of Barbara Hope Cooper, a Cornell University physics professor.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Barbara Hope Cooper, 1953-1999, Cornell Class of 1976, graduated Magna Cum Laude in Physics and with Distinction in all Subjects, with a B.A. degree in Physics; then attended graduate school at the California Institute of Technology until June 1982 when she received a Ph.D. in Physics. She returned to Cornell as an Assistant Professor of Physics in 1983, became an Associate Professor of Physics at Cornell in 1989, and a full Professor in 1995.
Her main research interests as an experimental physicist and a leader in surface science were:
1) the use of low-energy ion beams to probe particle-surface interactions and the structural and electronic features of clean and adsorbate-covered metal surfaces,
2) atomic-scale scanning tunneling microscopy studies of mass transport and stability of nanoscale structures on ion-bombarded metal surfaces,
3) in situ studies of surface roughening during bombardment using synchrotron x-rays.
She guided a dozen students through their doctorates at Cornell.
She worked for Bell Laboratories, Kellogg Radiation Laboratory at Cal Tech, and Cornell University. She was awarded an Avon Scholarship, 1971-1976; a Bell Laboratories Graduate Research Program for Women Grant, 1976-1981; a Presidential Young Investigator Award, 1985-1989, an IBM Faculty Development Award, 1985 and 1986; and the Maria Goeppert-Mayer Award of the American Physical Society, 1992. She was a member of the American Vacuum Society, Sigma Xi, Bohemian Physical Society and a fellow of the American Physical Society.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection includes correspondence, notes, calculations, materials for talks, data collection information, publication drafts and reprints, and course materials from student years as well as outlines, exams, and lab manuals used in teaching.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cooper, Barbara Hope, 1953-1999.; Cornell University. Class of 1976.
Subjects:
Physicists.; Physics--Study and teaching.; Women college teachers.; Women physicists.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 7 closed until 2080 - personnel records.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical Materials
Box 1
Series II. Honors
Box 1
Series III. Correspondence
Box 1
Series IV. Subject Files
Box 1
Series V. Student Coursework
Boxes 1-3
Series VI. Cornell: BHC no.s 1-6, 1983-1997
Boxes 3-4
Series VII. Conferences
Box 4
Series VIII. Publications
Box 4
Series IX. Talks
Box 5
Series X. Proposals
Box 5
Series XI. Grant
Box 5
Series XII. Teaching Materials
Box 6
Series XIII. Unprocessed Materials
Boxes 7-13
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Honors
  - Sigma Xi membership certificate, Cal Tech, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fellow American Physical Society (APS), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III. Correspondence
  - Bell Labs, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV. Subject Files
  - APS: March Meeting, 1992/Maria Goeppert Mayer, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - APS: March Meeting, 1992/CSWP panel discussion (Women Physicists), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - APS: March Meeting 1993, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - APS: DCMP (Division of Condensed Matter Physics) 1997-98, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - APS, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Beam Tests, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Burggraf Site Visit, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CHESS - Cornell Beamline, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Data Acquisition, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Data & Simulations, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Funding: Congress - DOD (Department of Defense) funding cuts 1994, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ho, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - IBM Faculty Development Award, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Juelich visit - IISC-II (Wangerooge), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Kellogg Sputtering Work, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 23-26)
  - Low Energy Ion Scattering, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - National Science Board, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pairing: Superfluids & Superconductors, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Presidential Young Investigators Awards, National Science Foundation, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Proton Decay, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - REU (Research Experience for Undergraduates), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Review of Scientific Instruments, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Sloan Nomination, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Structure (Notes), 1983+ (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - WIP (Women in Physics), 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Series V. Student Coursework
  - Cornell
    - Physics 325, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
    - Physics 341, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - Physics 318, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
    - Physics 443, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
    - Physics 551, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Physics 444, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Physics 444, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Physics 454, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Cal Tech
    - Physics 112, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Physics 129, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
    - Physics 209, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
    - Candidacy Exam, April, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Seminar Notes, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Sputtering Experiment Notes, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Physics 237, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
    - Experiment Data, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Seminar Notes, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Calculations and Notes, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Physics 230, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
    - Equipment/Ice Sputtering, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Bell Telephone Labs Trip (Notes & Data), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Physics 214, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Tandem Runs Book 2, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lit & Reading, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Calculations & Notes, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tandem Runs Books 3-5, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
    - Notes & Calculations, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Tandem Runs Book 6, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - BHC Thesis, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Thesis Figure Originals, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Thesis: Copy for Xerox, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Job Application Documents: CV, Reprints, etc., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Interview Trip May 1982, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Cornell 1982, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Cornell Negotiations & Arrangements, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series VI. Cornell: BHC no.s 1-6, 1983-1997
  - Cooper - 3 year review, etc., 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 6 Notebooks, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 22-27)
  - "Seminars" Notebook, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Physics 112, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Notes, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Physics 360, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Seminars III, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Seminars IV, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Physics 681, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Seminars V, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Notes, 1986[?] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes, n.d. (1983+) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notes, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4-9)
  - Notes: Research discussions, seminars, AT & T Trip, Univ. VA, Gordon - Particle Solid - 1990, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Notes: Mar. 16, 1992 - Apr. 22, 1992, also March Meeting 1992, Apr. 10, 1992 - CEX exp[erimen]ts to be done, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Notes: May 6, 1992 - Mar. 17, 1993, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Notes: May 1992, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Notes: Oct. 20, 1992 - Jun. 7, 1993, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Notes: Dec. 1992, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Notes: CEX, 1992(?) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Notes, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Notes: Jun. 8, 1993 - Nov. 30, 1993, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Notes: Dec. 1, 1993 - Jun. 20, 1994, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Notes: Jun. 20, 1994 - [Sep. 9, 1994], 1994 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Notes: [Aug. 1994], 1994 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Notes: Sep. 15, 1994 - [Dec. 1994], 1994 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Notes, 1994(?) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Notes: Dec. 1994 - Oct. 1995, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Notes, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Notes: Oct. 14, 1995 - Aug. 15, 1996, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Notes: Jun. 3, 1996 - Oct. 31, 1996, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Notes: May [no year], 1996 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Series VII. Conferences
  - Gordon Research Conference, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Gordon Research Conference [Georgetown]: Atomic Collisions in Solids, "Gas Surface Dynamic," Colby-Sawyer, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Gordon Research Conference: Dynamics at Surfaces, Aug. 6-11, 1995, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Gordon Research Conference, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Gordon Research Conference: "Materials Processes Far From Equilibrium" (viewgraph originals), 1997 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Liverpool, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - McMaster University Conference, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - March Meeting, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - March Meeting, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - March Meeting, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - March Meeting, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
  - March Meeting, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Series VIII. Publications
  - List of Publications, 1980-1996 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - A-C, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - D, 1987-1997 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - E, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
  - L-M, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - O-P, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - RSI (Keller), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - R-T, 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Macmillan Encyclopedia of Physics, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 52-54)
- Series IX. Talks
  - Cal Tech Talks, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cal Tech Talks (thesis drawings), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - FCP (Fractionally Charged Particles) talk to PH 10 12/7/82, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Gordon Research Conference, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - March Meeting, 1988(?) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notes, figures, Post 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Notes, figures, Post 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Northwestern, 1992(?) (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Cornell Colloquium, September, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Cornell Colloquium, October, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Cornell Colloquium: Cornell, Penn, NIST, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Notes, figures, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 13-19)
- Series X. Proposals
  - MSC (Materials Science Center), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 20-28)
  - MSC: 1 yr + 3 yr proposal/surface group summary, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - NSF (National Science Foundation), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - AFOSR/NC, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 31-33)
  - MSC, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - MSC, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 35-40)
- Series XI. Grant
  - NSF Young Investigator Award, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
- Series XII. Teaching Materials
  - Physics 112 exams, 1984-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Physics 112 Laboratory Manual, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 3-6)
  - Physics 208, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - Physics 213, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Physics 213, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Physics 360, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 11-17)
  - A & EP (Applied and Engineering Physics) 662, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Aaron Judy (graduate assistant), 1997-1999 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Series XIII. Unprocessed Materials (Box 7-13)